
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>This is my blog...</title>
   <link>https://sallyom.github.io/</link>
   <description>Recent content on This is my blog...</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2020-2025 - Sally Ann O&#39;Malley</copyright>
   <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
   
       <atom:link href="https://sallyom.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>AI Is 1000× Better Than Me at Writing Code (And I&#39;m Not Threatened by That)</title>
       <link>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/deeper-dive-into-how-i-partner-with-ai/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 10:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/deeper-dive-into-how-i-partner-with-ai/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;I recently made a statement to my team and broader organization that had mixedreactions. I said: &amp;ldquo;AI is a thousand times better than me at writing code.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;There was a pause. A few raised eyebrows. Some polite skepticism. A sense thatI had either exaggerated wildly or accidentally declared myself obsolete.So I want to explain what I meant, because I stand by it. And also because itabsolutely does not mean I have been replaced or am relaxing comfortably on abeach somewhere, sipping a mint julep.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-actually-meant&#34;&gt;What I &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; meant&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I say AI is dramatically better than me at writing code, I am talking veryspecifically about the mechanics of writing code. I haven&amp;rsquo;t gathered data to back the &amp;ldquo;1000x&amp;rdquo; claim,I&amp;rsquo;m going with how it feels. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about the boilerplate, tests, formatting, syntax, translations between languages and versions, and setup.The repetitive shapes I have written a hundred times before. In that narrow domain, yes, AI is astonishingly good.But writing code is one small part of my job. And now, I can spend more time on the more interesting parts.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI has not removed my role. It has changed where my attention goes.I am not doing &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; work. I am doing &lt;em&gt;different&lt;/em&gt; work. In many ways, more demanding work.The cognitive load didn’t disappear, it shifted upward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-this-looks-like-in-practice&#34;&gt;What this looks like in practice&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have been working on observability for &lt;a href=&#34;https://llm-d.ai/&#34;&gt;llm-d&lt;/a&gt;, an open source Kubernetes-native high-performancedistributed LLM inference framework. It&amp;rsquo;s a complex ecosystem with multiple components, repositories, compatible LLMs,and endless hardware configurations and options. The debugging and performance behaviors vary dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Through several Slack threads and conversations with the core domain experts, wecompiled a document listing the most important observability insights — thesignals engineers rely on to understand a running llm-d system.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I opened a session with Claude, gave it access to the llm-d repositories, andshared the document. In less than an hour, and through a fully engaged, iterative conversation, the AI:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;scanned all relevant codebases&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;mapped each desired insight to the exact metrics available&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;wrote precise PromQL queries for each one&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;identified where metrics were missing&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;suggested new metric additions, complete with cardinality analysis&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;and generated a ready-to-import Grafana dashboard&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We then produced documentation explaining what each query shows, when itmatters, and why. I&amp;rsquo;m currently approaching llm-d distributed tracing in a similar way.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This wasn&amp;rsquo;t AI replacing engineers. This was AI working alongside us, amplifying the expertise of humans who knowthis system deeply. This is what “1000× better at writing code” means in practice. Acceleration, not displacement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;partnership-not-replacement&#34;&gt;Partnership, not replacement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The best way I can describe this is that AI is not a substitute engineer. It isa partner. A fast, tireless, deeply knowledgeable partner who, in my experience:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;never gets bored&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;does not get defensive&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;can rewrite something ten different ways&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;is always available&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;can switch languages instantly&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;and does not mind being wrong&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;But it does not decide what matters. It does not know the constraints of a real system or organization. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand context, tradeoffs,or consequences. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t magically make an unskilled developer a wizard. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t replace the skills I&amp;rsquo;ve acquired writing code over the lastdecade without it. It makes my talent and skills more accessible. It does not own outcomes. I do. My team does. Humans do.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ai-is-not-our-competitor&#34;&gt;AI is not our competitor&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is something deeper here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI is not an alien intellect intruding on human work. It is a reflection of us.It is built from our words, our ideas, our patterns, our creativity, ourhistory. In a very real sense, it is human.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;A model is a compression of everything we have written, discovered,documented, debated, and imagined. When we collaborate with AI, we are notengaging a foreign intelligence. We are accessing a distilled, pattern-richmemory of what humanity already knows.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI is not here to replace us.It cannot replace us. It is powered by us, shaped by us, limited by us, and elevated by us.It extends human capability. It does not compete with it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;And I genuinely believe the amount of “better” it brings is infinitely largerthan the amount of “worse.” Not because AI is inherently good, but becausehumans are, and when given better tools, (eventually) reach for better possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI is not distancing us from the work.&lt;br&gt;It is bringing us closer to the parts that matter.This is the world I choose to live in and to continuously work toward. I simply refuse to accept any other reality.And it really is that simple.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>Two Ways Developers Approach a Problem</title>
       <link>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/there-are-two-types-of-developers/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/there-are-two-types-of-developers/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;When you give two software engineers the same problem, you can often predict what they&amp;rsquo;ll do next, regardless of seniority or skill level.Developers usually follow one of two instincts. One instinct is motion. Make something happen as quickly as possible. Open an editor,wire things together, push until the system does &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; at all. It doesn’t have to be elegant or correct, it just has to exist. For thesedevelopers, forward motion creates clarity. Code is how they ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The other instinct is understanding. Slow down. Ask questions. Read the docs. Sketch diagrams. Build a complete mental model before writing aline of code. For these developers, code isn’t a tool for discovery, it’s an expression of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neither instinct is better. They simply optimize for different risks: never starting versus building the wrong thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been firmly in the first camp. When I’m given a problem, my instinct isn’t to fully understand it. I need to make &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; happen.Anything. Even if it’s wrong. Even if all the computer does is print “hello world.” Once something exists, once it runs, crashes, or behavesbadly, I can move forward. That’s how I think, trial and error code is how I ask questions. It turns out that AI works well with this style of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-ai-fits-this-style-well&#34;&gt;Why AI fits this style well&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI lowers the cost of that first step. The time between “I wonder if this could work” and “I havesomething I can react to” has nearly collapsed. I don’t have to fight syntax, imports, or setup just to get a pulse. Ican describe what I want, see it come alive almost instantly, and then start refining. For someone wired the way I am,that changes everything and it makes me feel somewhat superhuman.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-part-ive-always-struggled-to-explain&#34;&gt;The part I’ve always struggled to explain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s another aspect of how I work that I’ve never been comfortable naming. Sometimes I can deliver exactly the rightsolution to a problem without being able to fully articulate how I arrived there. Not because I don’t understand it,but because the understanding doesn’t live in words. It lives in interaction, feedback, and feel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Much of my knowledge lives in pattern recognition and motion. I can produce correct behavior without being able to fullylinearize the reasoning afterward. That has occasionally been mistaken for me not knowing what I’m talking about. I cansee how it looks that way. I don’t enjoy dissecting every detail or narrating every decision after the fact. That kind ofanalysis has never been what drives me. To me, it often feels like reiterating what already exists rather than movingtoward something new.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I’m actually trying to understand isn’t the implementation, but it’s the behavior of the system. How does itrespond when I poke it? How does it fail? How does it change under pressure, load, or constraints?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once I can feel that shape, I can usually guide it where it needs to go. And sometimes that understanding resists aclean explanation. It’s closer to intuition than logic, closer to art than science. For a long time, I worried that thismeant I was missing something fundamental. Now I’m starting to think it just means I operate differently. Not every form ofunderstanding needs to be narratable to be real.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-teams-need-both-intuition-and-articulation&#34;&gt;Why teams need both intuition and articulation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though intuition is how I naturally learn and build, I’m very aware that it isn’t sufficient on its own,especially when considering the success of a team. I’m more than happy to engage in detailed discussions. I care aboutdesign reviews, diagrams, proposals, and shared understanding. I know it’s my responsibility to read them, follow them,and usually abide by them. Those artifacts matter. They’re how teams align, how decisions scale, and how work survives beyondany one person. It’s just not how I start. I&amp;rsquo;ll never kick off a project by presenting a perfectly formedmermaid diagram. My brain seems to have a kind of dyslexia when it even comes to reading them. I need to see somethingbehave before the structure clicks. That doesn’t mean the structure isn’t important. It just means I arrive at it from theopposite direction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, I’ve learned that strong teams need both instincts. They need people who can feel their way throughambiguity and make something real quickly and they need people who can slow things down, articulate the shape of thesystem, and make it legible to everyone else. Intuition without articulation doesn’t scale. Articulation withoutintuition doesn’t move. The magic happens when the two meet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ai-as-a-bridge-not-a-replacement&#34;&gt;AI as a bridge, not a replacement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I’m starting to realize is that AI doesn’t favor one style of thinking over the other. It can act as a bridgebetween them. For someone like me, AI gives shape to intuition. I can start with a feeling, a nudge, a rough idea ofbehavior, and turn it into something concrete quickly. Once something exists, it becomes easier for me, and for others, totalk about it, reason about it, and eventually formalize it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the bridge works in the other direction too. AI is good at turning intuition into articulation. It can help namehalf-formed ideas, generate diagrams, write proposals, summarize behavior, and translate “this feels right” intolanguage others can engage with. It doesn’t replace shared artifacts, it lowers the friction of creating them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In that sense, AI doesn’t erase the need for design or documentation. It makes them more accessible to people whose brainsdon’t naturally start there. And for teams, that matters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;and-it-serves-the-other-style-too&#34;&gt;And it serves the other style, too&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a one-way bridge. AI doesn’t just help intuition-driven developers like me articulate our thinking. It alsosupports developers whose instinct is to understand everything first.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For model-first thinkers, AI becomes a tireless thought partner. It can explore edge cases, validate assumptions,pressure-test designs, and surface inconsistencies long before any code is written. It rewards careful specification.It responds well to precise constraints. It can reason through alternatives and help refine a mental model beforecommitting to an implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What changes most is the cost of iteration. Model-first developers no longer have to hold everything perfectly in theirheads before testing an idea. They can ask “what if?” safely. They can explore variants without throwing away hours of work.They can move fluidly between reasoning and experimentation without betraying their natural approach. AI doesn’t ask themto abandon rigor. It gives them a faster feedback loop for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both styles keep their identity. Both gain leverage. The goal was never for everyone to think the same way. The goal wasalways to build things together. AI gives us a new surface to meet on. A way for intuition and articulation to informeach other instead of competing. That feels less like a disruption and more like a translation layer. Whether you canfeel it or not, AI has changed forever what is possible with software development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>I Didn&#39;t Change Jobs - AI Changed the Job I Have</title>
       <link>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/i-have-a-new-job/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/i-have-a-new-job/</guid>
       <description>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months, my role as a software developer has profoundly transformed.I didn&amp;rsquo;t negotiate a new title or adopt a new framework. Without ceremony or fanfare, the job itself simply changed.With AI&amp;rsquo;s quiet and reliable power, old workflows have become obsolete.Not using AI stopped making sense. The ground moved beneath me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I didn’t decide to work differently. AI became too good to ignore.I used to write everything from scratch: a Kubernetes controller, a bash script,a system manifest. That was the job. Today, I describe that same controller’s desiredbehavior to an AI, and it generates the entire, clean codebase, complete withscaffolding, RBAC, and tests. It’s not just generating code; it’s providing instantaccess to a compressed universe of accumulated patterns and knowledge.What&amp;rsquo;s more, when the model understands the workflow, and I can give it a runner or tool access,executing code can often become redundant. We can now bypass code entirely by delegating behaviorin plain text to an AI runner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t theory; it&amp;rsquo;s my daily workflow. Every refactor, script, and debuggingsession now starts with my AI partner. I still write code, but I often find myself questioning whether something should even be atraditional codebase or whether a conversational interface with a tool-runner is sufficient. I think about where I needdeterminism and where flexibility is acceptable; what deserves to be a strict function and what can be an AI-guidedworkflow; what constraints the system needs and what architecture will keep it safe, predictable, and adaptable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another thing, I can’t prepare students or mentor junior engineers the way I used to. For the past 5 years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been teaching a course at Boston University,&lt;em&gt;Software Engineering Career Prep&lt;/em&gt;. I share with aspiring data and computer scientists what I do every day. This fall my class syllabus became amoving target. The profession they&amp;rsquo;re entering is already vastly different from what it was even last semester.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The old rhythm of the job, sketching ideas into code over a few days or weeks, creating tests and documentation,wrestling with git - that world is fading. It&amp;rsquo;s not gone, but it&amp;rsquo;s no longer the center.Their success won&amp;rsquo;t hinge on how fast they can write, but on how well they can think, specify, and define a problem.It always should have been this way, but the mechanics of implementing code has until now been a large factor in early career success.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Strangely enough, I firmly believe the human part of my job is getting stronger. As AI takes on more of the rogue parentheses and uneven whitespace,the nil-pointer and race condition hunts, the repetitive boilerplate, I can imagine a world where my teammates and I spend more time actually talking.More time imagining and designing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we’re less hunched over keyboards we can be more engaged with each other. When the tedious parts aren’t draining our energy,we may have more space to explore ideas that once felt too ambitious or too time-consuming. Wild ideas feel more doable.Innovative solutions feel closer. The ceiling feels higher.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which is fitting, because even this post was written the same way I now build software: in conversation with my AI partner,shaping the ideas together, clarifying them like I would with a colleague or a very patient friend.The process even feels a little like therapy for the engineering mind: a space to think out loud, challenge assumptions,and imagine what could be possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This post is simply a marker in time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The job has changed. It changed in the last eight weeks. It changed in the fewdays I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing this post. Avoiding AI stopped making sense. This is themoment I realized software engineering is being rewritten. Everything that followsstarts here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
