
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="https://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Adventures in Open Sourcery</title>
   <link>https://commandtheline.com/</link>
   <description>Recent content on Adventures in Open Sourcery</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2020 - Sally Ann O&#39;Malley</copyright>
   <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 23:57:50 -0400</lastBuildDate>
   
       <atom:link href="https://commandtheline.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>Allow Me to Introduce Myself</title>
       <link>https://commandtheline.com/posts/allow-me-to-introduce-myself/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2020 23:57:50 -0400</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://commandtheline.com/posts/allow-me-to-introduce-myself/</guid>
       <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been working as a software engineer for a while now.  I&amp;rsquo;m a mom.  This is
my blog.  How did I get here?  Back up to around the time Linux became a thing.
I was at Northeastern University, a double major in Chemical Engineering
and Biology.  This is my blog so I can brag.  I was at NU on a full academic
scholarship.  I made some good friends, earned good grades, was inducted into
Tau Beta Pi, the National Honor Society of Engineers (that&amp;rsquo;s so when I
tell you the next part, you don&amp;rsquo;t assume I flunked out of engineering).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not want to be a Chemical Engineer. I threw away the final year
of my scholarship to graduate a year early with a generic biology degree with
which I could do very little.  I had taken a few painting courses along the
way and I was going to be an artist, live out of a backpack, whatever that
means. I met my husband.  I studied Sanskrit. I learned to play the flute.
I moved to Napa, CA.  I traveled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My father was diagnosed with cancer, with 3-6 months to live.
He passed away 5 months later.  I spent those months with him in Maine.
I was forced to question my place in the universe, and what it was I was
meant to do here.  I felt the need to stop puttering around and figure
that out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward five years.  I was now the mother of a beautiful daughter and
baby boy.  I loved and still love being a mom and a wife.  I was plagued
with the notion that there was something else I was meant to do, that my
education was incomplete.  This feeling was constant and tiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one class at Northeastern I loved the most. It was a fluid mechanics
course, during which I wrote my first computer program.  I taught myself just
enough C to complete an assignment.  I remember sitting in a computer lab
for hours, tracking down rogue parentheses and semicolons. I remember the
feeling of victory when I entered some tank measurements, pipe diameters, and
viscosities, and my program output the time it would take to empty the tank.
That memory is the reason I enrolled at UMass, to study as many programming
courses as I could afford, and ended up with a degree in Information Technology and
an internship at Red Hat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first two weeks at Red Hat I learned git.  My first pull request merged,
it was a README addition.  I noticed there weren&amp;rsquo;t many women engineers.  I mean,
there &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; were not many women engineers. That&amp;rsquo;s all I can say about that.
I&amp;rsquo;m not here to solve that problem, not yet.
I&amp;rsquo;m learning some things new every single day.  I&amp;rsquo;ll keep learning,
to be a mentor for anyone who comes in behind me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of mentors, I&amp;rsquo;ve had many.  I graduated from intern to associate software
engineer to software engineer.  I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to work with some brilliant people whose
ideas are shaping the future.  I want to share some of the cool things I&amp;rsquo;ve learned
from working with lots of really smart people.  Lately it&amp;rsquo;s been Kubernetes and
OpenShift but I try to mix it up a bit.  I&amp;rsquo;m living my dream.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>PR Checkout No Remote</title>
       <link>https://commandtheline.com/posts/git-checkout-no-remote/</link>
       <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2020 00:16:29 -0400</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://commandtheline.com/posts/git-checkout-no-remote/</guid>
       <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;you-dont-have-to-add-a-remote-to-checkout-a-pull-request-or-a-friends-branch&#34;&gt;You don&amp;rsquo;t have to add a remote to checkout a Pull Request or a friend&amp;rsquo;s branch!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you already know this, then move along.
Whenever I mention to somebody about how I check out a branch to review a PR, 99% of the time,
they thank me and say, &lt;code&gt;I&#39;ve always just added a new remote! This is way faster, thanks!&lt;/code&gt; I
figured, then, that this would be a good little blog post, if I ever got around to creating my
blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say you are tasked with reviewing a colleague&amp;rsquo;s pull request, &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; your friend has a much
needed feature in their branch that you want to take advantage of &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; there&amp;rsquo;s a pull
request.  What do you do? If you don&amp;rsquo;t do this, you&amp;rsquo;re probably doing it the hard way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The repositories mentioned here do not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assume you have your fork of cool-repo checked out locally, and you need to work with
your friend&amp;rsquo;s branch of cool-repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, here&amp;rsquo;s the little bit of convenience:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd cool-repo

$ git fetch git@github.com:your-friend/cool-repo.git much-needed-branch

$ git checkout FETCH_HEAD
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now, you&amp;rsquo;ll be in detached mode, and if you&amp;rsquo;re simply reviewing a PR, go ahead and work from there.
However, if you&amp;rsquo;ll be messing around and making changes in this branch, you can create a
full-fledged branch by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git checkout -b now-it-is-my-much-needed-branch&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it! Hope I save you a few seconds of adding/deleting remotes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
