
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Categories on This is my blog...</title>
   <link>https://sallyom.github.io/categories/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Categories on This is my blog...</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2020-2025 - Sally Ann O&#39;Malley</copyright>
   
       <atom:link href="https://sallyom.github.io/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>I Didn&#39;t Change Jobs - AI Changed the Job I Have</title>
       <link>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/i-have-a-new-job/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/i-have-a-new-job/</guid>
       <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;i-didnt-change-jobs---ai-changed-the-job-i-have&#34;&gt;I Didn&amp;rsquo;t Change Jobs - AI Changed the Job I Have&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-the-last-few-months-quietly-transformed-my-role-as-a-software-engineer&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How the last few months quietly transformed my role as a software engineer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last &lt;strong&gt;eight weeks&lt;/strong&gt;, my role as a software developer has quietly andprofoundly transformed. I didn&amp;rsquo;t negotiate a new title or adopt a new framework. Withoutceremony or fanfare, the job itself simply changed. With AI, old workflows have become obsolete.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-didnt-decide-to-work-differently-ai-became-too-good-to-ignore&#34;&gt;I didn’t decide to work differently. AI became too good to ignore.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I used to write everything from scratch: a Kubernetes controller, a complex script,a system manifest. That was the job. Today, I describe that same controller’s desiredbehavior to an AI, and it generates the entire, clean codebase, complete withscaffolding, RBAC, and tests. It’s not just generating code; it’s providing instantaccess to a compressed universe of accumulated patterns and knowledge. What I wasn&amp;rsquo;tprepared for was its &lt;strong&gt;quiet, reliable power&lt;/strong&gt;. For many tasks, we now bypass codeentirely, delegating the workflow itself to the AI.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t theory; it&amp;rsquo;s my daily workflow. Every refactor, script, and debuggingsession now starts with my AI partner. Before, building a complex Grafana dashboardmeant tedious manual work, digging through multiple repos for metrics. Now, I askthe AI to scan all components, extract every metric, and generate a full, insightfuldashboard in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I still write code, but &lt;strong&gt;I often find myself questioning whether something should even be atraditional codebase or whether a conversational interface with a tool-runner is sufficient&lt;/strong&gt;. I think about where I needdeterminism and where flexibility is acceptable; what deserves to be a strict function and what can be an AI-guidedworkflow; what constraints the system needs and what architecture will keep it safe, predictable, and adaptable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-cant-prepare-students-for-the-profession-the-way-i-used-to&#34;&gt;I can’t prepare students for the profession the way I used to.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I teach a college course in the evenings, &lt;em&gt;Software Engineering Career Prep&lt;/em&gt;.I share with aspiring data and computer scientists what I do every day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This semester, something shook me: I can no longer prepare students for the profession the way Iused to. Not because they don&amp;rsquo;t need fundamentals - they absolutely do - but because the profession they&amp;rsquo;re entering is alreadyvastly different from what it was even last semester.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The old rhythm of the job, sketching ideas into code over a few days or weeks, creating tests and documentation,wrestling with git - that world is fading. It&amp;rsquo;s not gone, but it&amp;rsquo;s no longer the center.Their success won&amp;rsquo;t hinge on how fast they can write, but on how well they can &lt;strong&gt;think, specify, and define a problem&lt;/strong&gt;.It always should have been this way, but the mechanics of implementing code has until now been a large factor in early career success.Even the most junior engineers will spend more time architecting code than typing it.Realizing this as a mentor and teacher is what made the shift undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;and-strangely-enough-the-human-part-of-my-job-got-stronger&#34;&gt;And strangely enough, the human part of my job got stronger.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As AI takes on more of the mechanical labor, the rogue parentheses and unwanted whitespace, the nil-pointer and race condition hunts,the repetitive boilerplate, my teammates and I spend more time actually talking. More time imagining. More time designing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re less hunched over keyboards and more engaged with each other. And because the tedious parts aren&amp;rsquo;t draining ourenergy, we all have more space to explore ideas that once felt too ambitious or too time-consuming. Wild ideas feelmore doable. Innovative solutions feel closer. The ceiling feels higher.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which is fitting, because even this post was written the same way I now build software: in conversation with my AIpartner, shaping the ideas together, clarifying them like I would with a colleague or a very patient friend. Theprocess even feels a little like therapy for the engineering mind: a space to think out loud, challenge assumptions,and imagine what could be possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-post-is-simply-a-marker-in-time&#34;&gt;This post is simply a marker in time.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The job has changed. It changed in the last eight weeks. It changed in the fewdays I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing this post.&lt;/strong&gt; Avoiding AI stopped making sense. This is themoment I realized software engineering is being rewritten. Everything that followsstarts here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
