
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 <channel>
   <title>Categories on This is my blog...</title>
   <link>https://sallyom.github.io/categories/</link>
   <description>Recent content in Categories on This is my blog...</description>
   <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
   <language>en</language>
   <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; 2020-2025 - Sally Ann O&#39;Malley</copyright>
   
       <atom:link href="https://sallyom.github.io/categories/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
   
     <item>
       <title>There Are Two Types of Software Developers</title>
       <link>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/there-are-two-types-of-developers/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/there-are-two-types-of-developers/</guid>
       <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;there-are-two-types-of-software-developers&#34;&gt;There Are Two Types of Software Developers&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;When you give two software engineers the same problem, you can often predict what they’ll do next not by seniority orskill level, but by instinct. Over time, I’ve come to believe there are two broad styles of developers. These aren’trigid categories, and most of us move between them depending on context. But under pressure, we tend to default to one. Thedifference shows up immediately after a problem is handed over.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-instincts&#34;&gt;Two instincts&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The first kind of developer responds to a new problem with motion. They want to &lt;em&gt;do something&lt;/em&gt; as quickly as possible.They open an editor, scaffold a project, wire pieces together, often with copy and paste, and push forward until thesystem does anything at all. It doesn’t have to be elegant. It doesn’t even have to be correct. It just has to exist.For this kind of developer, forward motion creates clarity. Understanding emerges through interaction.Code is how they ask the system questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The second kind of developer reacts very differently. Faced with a problem, they slow down. They ask questions.They want to understand every input, every constraint, every edge case before writing a single line of code.They sketch diagrams, read documentation, and build a complete mental model first. For them, code is not a tool fordiscovery, it’s an expression of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Neither instinct is better. They simply optimize for different risks. One minimizes the risk of never starting.The other minimizes the risk of building the wrong thing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;where-i-land&#34;&gt;Where I land&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been firmly in the first camp. When I’m given a problem, my instinct isn’t to fully understand it.It’s to make &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; happen. Anything. Even if it’s wrong. Even if it’s trivial. Even if all the computer does isprint “hello world.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I need to know that I can make the system respond to me, that I can get &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; foothold at all. Once something exists,once it runs, prints, crashes, or behaves badly, I can move forward. That’s how I think. Code is how I ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-ai-fits-this-style-well&#34;&gt;Why AI fits this style well&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;AI dramatically lowers the cost of that first step. The time between “I wonder if this could work” and “I havesomething I can react to” has nearly collapsed. I don’t have to fight syntax, imports, or setup just to get a pulse. Ican describe what I want, see it come alive almost instantly, and then start refining. For someone wired the way I am,that changes everything. What surprised me wasn’t that AI could write code, but how well it matched the way I already think.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-part-ive-always-struggled-to-explain&#34;&gt;The part I’ve always struggled to explain&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There’s another aspect of how I work that I’ve never been comfortable naming. Sometimes I can deliver exactly the rightsolution to a problem without being able to fully articulate how I arrived there. Not because I don’t understand it,but because the understanding doesn’t live in words. It lives in interaction, feedback, and feel.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Much of my knowledge lives in pattern recognition and motion. I can produce correct behavior without being able to fullylinearize the reasoning afterward. That has occasionally been mistaken for me not knowing what I’m talking about. I cansee how it looks that way. I don’t enjoy dissecting every detail or narrating every decision after the fact. That kind ofanalysis has never been what drives me. To me, it often feels like reiterating what already exists rather than movingtoward something new.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I’m actually trying to understand isn’t the implementation, but it’s the behavior of the system. How does itrespond when I poke it? How does it fail? How does it change under pressure, load, or constraints?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Once I can feel that shape, I can usually guide it where it needs to go. And sometimes that understanding resists aclean explanation. It’s closer to intuition than logic, closer to art than science. For a long time, I worried that thismeant I was missing something fundamental. Now I’m starting to think it just means I operate differently. Not every form ofunderstanding needs to be narratable to be real.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-teams-need-both-intuition-and-articulation&#34;&gt;Why teams need both intuition and articulation&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though intuition is how I naturally learn and build, I’m very aware that it isn’t sufficient on its own,especially when considering the success of a team. I’m more than happy to engage in detailed discussions. I care aboutdesign reviews, diagrams, proposals, and shared understanding. I know it’s my responsibility to read them, follow them,and usually abide by them. Those artifacts matter. They’re how teams align, how decisions scale, and how work survives beyondany one person. It’s just not how I start. You’ll never find me kicking off a project by presenting a perfectly formedmermaid diagram. My brain almost seems to have a kind of dyslexia when it comes to reading them. I need to see somethingbehave before the structure clicks. That doesn’t mean the structure isn’t important. It just means I arrive at it from theopposite direction.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over time, I’ve learned that strong teams need both instincts. They need people who can feel their way throughambiguity and make something real quickly and they need people who can slow things down, articulate the shape of thesystem, and make it legible to everyone else. Intuition without articulation doesn’t scale. Articulation withoutintuition doesn’t move. The magic happens when the two meet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;ai-as-a-bridge-not-a-replacement&#34;&gt;AI as a bridge, not a replacement&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I’m starting to realize is that AI doesn’t favor one style of thinking over the other. It can act as a bridgebetween them. For someone like me, AI gives shape to intuition. I can start with a feeling, a nudge, a rough idea ofbehavior, and turn it into something concrete quickly. Once something exists, it becomes easier for me, and for others, totalk about it, reason about it, and eventually formalize it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;But the bridge works in the other direction too. AI is good at turning intuition into articulation. It can help namehalf-formed ideas, generate diagrams, write proposals, summarize behavior, and translate “this feels right” intolanguage others can engage with. It doesn’t replace shared artifacts, it lowers the friction of creating them.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;In that sense, AI doesn’t erase the need for design or documentation. It makes them more accessible to people whose brainsdon’t naturally start there. And for teams, that matters.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;and-it-serves-the-other-style-too&#34;&gt;And it serves the other style, too&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a one-way bridge. AI doesn’t just help intuition-driven developers like me articulate our thinking. It alsosupports developers whose instinct is to understand everything first.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;For model-first thinkers, AI becomes a tireless thought partner. It can explore edge cases, validate assumptions,pressure-test designs, and surface inconsistencies long before any code is written. It rewards careful specification.It responds well to precise constraints. It can reason through alternatives and help refine a mental model beforecommitting to an implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;What changes most is the cost of iteration. Model-first developers no longer have to hold everything perfectly in theirheads before testing an idea. They can ask “what if?” safely. They can explore variants without throwing away hours of work.They can move fluidly between reasoning and experimentation without betraying their natural approach. AI doesn’t ask themto abandon rigor. It gives them a faster feedback loop for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both styles keep their identity. Both gain leverage. The goal was never for everyone to think the same way. The goal wasalways to build things together. AI gives us a new surface to meet on. A way for intuition and articulation to informeach other instead of competing. That feels less like a disruption and more like a translation layer. Whether you canfeel it or not, AI has changed forever what is possible with software development.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
     <item>
       <title>I Didn&#39;t Change Jobs - AI Changed the Job I Have</title>
       <link>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/i-have-a-new-job/</link>
       <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 20:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
       
       <guid>https://sallyom.github.io/posts/i-have-a-new-job/</guid>
       <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;i-didnt-change-jobs---ai-changed-the-job-i-have&#34;&gt;I Didn&amp;rsquo;t Change Jobs - AI Changed the Job I Have&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-the-last-few-months-quietly-transformed-my-role-as-a-software-engineer&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How the last few months quietly transformed my role as a software engineer&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the last &lt;strong&gt;eight weeks&lt;/strong&gt;, my role as a software developer has profoundly transformed.I didn&amp;rsquo;t negotiate a new title or adopt a new framework. Without ceremony or fanfare, the job itself simply changed.With AI&amp;rsquo;s quiet and reliable power, old workflows have become obsolete.Not using AI stopped making sense. The ground moved beneath me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-didnt-decide-to-work-differently-ai-became-too-good-to-ignore&#34;&gt;I didn’t decide to work differently. AI became too good to ignore.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I used to write everything from scratch: a Kubernetes controller, a complex script,a system manifest. That was the job. Today, I describe that same controller’s desiredbehavior to an AI, and it generates the entire, clean codebase, complete withscaffolding, RBAC, and tests. It’s not just generating code; it’s providing instantaccess to a compressed universe of accumulated patterns and knowledge.What&amp;rsquo;s more, when the model understands the workflow, and I can give it a runner or tool access,executing code can often become redundant. We can now bypass code entirely by delegating behaviorin plain text to an AI runner.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t theory; it&amp;rsquo;s my daily workflow. Every refactor, script, and debuggingsession now starts with my AI partner. Before, building a complex Grafana dashboardmeant tedious manual work, digging through multiple repos for metrics. Now, I askthe AI to scan all components, extract every metric, and generate a full, insightfuldashboard in minutes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I still write code, but &lt;strong&gt;I often find myself questioning whether something should even be atraditional codebase or whether a conversational interface with a tool-runner is sufficient&lt;/strong&gt;. I think about where I needdeterminism and where flexibility is acceptable; what deserves to be a strict function and what can be an AI-guidedworkflow; what constraints the system needs and what architecture will keep it safe, predictable, and adaptable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-cant-prepare-students-for-the-profession-the-way-i-used-to&#34;&gt;I can’t prepare students for the profession the way I used to.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I teach a college course in the evenings, &lt;em&gt;Software Engineering Career Prep&lt;/em&gt;.I share with aspiring data and computer scientists what I do every day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;This semester, something shook me: I can no longer prepare students for the profession the way Iused to. Not because they don&amp;rsquo;t need fundamentals - they absolutely do - but because the profession they&amp;rsquo;re entering is alreadyvastly different from what it was even last semester.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;The old rhythm of the job, sketching ideas into code over a few days or weeks, creating tests and documentation,wrestling with git - that world is fading. It&amp;rsquo;s not gone, but it&amp;rsquo;s no longer the center.Their success won&amp;rsquo;t hinge on how fast they can write, but on how well they can &lt;strong&gt;think, specify, and define a problem&lt;/strong&gt;.It always should have been this way, but the mechanics of implementing code has until now been a large factor in early career success.Even the most junior engineers will spend more time architecting code than typing it.Realizing this as a mentor and teacher is what made the shift undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;and-strangely-enough-the-human-part-of-my-job-got-stronger&#34;&gt;And strangely enough, the human part of my job got stronger.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As AI takes on more of the mechanical labor, the rogue parentheses, the nil-pointer and race condition hunts, the repetitive boilerplate,I can imagine a world where my teammates and I spend more time actually talking. More time imagining. More time designing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;When we’re less hunched over keyboards we can be more engaged with each other. When the tedious parts aren’t draining our energy,we may have more space to explore ideas that once felt too ambitious or too time-consuming. Wild ideas feel more doable.Innovative solutions feel closer. The ceiling feels higher.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Which is fitting, because even this post was written the same way I now build software: in conversation with my AI partner,shaping the ideas together, clarifying them like I would with a colleague or a very patient friend.The process even feels a little like therapy for the engineering mind: a space to think out loud, challenge assumptions,and imagine what could be possible.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;h2 id=&#34;this-post-is-simply-a-marker-in-time&#34;&gt;This post is simply a marker in time.&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The job has changed. It changed in the last eight weeks. It changed in the fewdays I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing this post.&lt;/strong&gt; Avoiding AI stopped making sense. This is themoment I realized software engineering is being rewritten. Everything that followsstarts here.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;</description>
     </item>
   
 </channel>
</rss>
